i'm ready
okay
hope that this
is working well and i guess this is
where we can begin the conversation
this is a twitter spaces on september 14
2022.
it is called can web 3 survive without
cognitive modeling and i know there's
something they say about headlines that
end in a question mark something like
always their yes answers or no answers
or
in this conversation we're going to be
talking about web 3 and about cognitive
modeling and
it will be less than an hour long
hopefully will serve as a nice
introduction to those who have
little or some familiarity with web3 and
cognitive modeling
alone or together but it's also meant to
be kind of a broad ranging discussion
and hopefully we'll have some other
voices come up and add in some thoughts
and questions
let's start with just a description of
web3
surely elsewhere you'll be able to find
audio and other kinds of content
describing web3 so
i'll just describe what's relevant about
it as we
talk about cognitive modeling web3
web 3 is an ongoing movements that is
applying blockchain and other
distributed technologies to a wide
ranging
areas
and we can think of web 3 as creating
critical infrastructure of the public
goods type or not necessarily public
goods in a wide
range of areas so in finance there's
decentralized finance or d5
and d5 requires the engineering of token
schemes which is sometimes called token
engineering or tokenomics
such that those token-based systems are
able to be designed effectively and
operate effectively and there's a lot of
other areas outside of the financial
that are important for web3 for example
community governance and meta governance
like what people may have heard about
dao's decentralized autonomous
organizations as well as all other kinds
of organizations
and
of particular interest for
our institute and for many others is
decentralized science or doosan
and in many ways desai will succeed
if it can have a balanced and coherent
approach
to tackle all the challenges
that face
the research and education stack ranging
from the who what why where when etc
our question that we'll return to
is how can any of these areas finance
community research science and education
how can any of these areas
be successfully navigated or designed
for without taking agents into account
so this is
very related to agent-based modeling and
we're going to explore how there are
several approaches to modeling these
complex systems
and we're going to suggest that
complementing top-down structural
modeling of these systems there's a
really important role for agentic or
what we can consider cognitive modeling
of the actors in these systems
themselves
and we believe that without this kind of
like a bottom-up
individual driven account
taken
conceptually
in to the design process but also more
formally into the specification and
evaluation of these critical
infrastructure systems
that there are going to be a lot of
blind spots and a lot of failure modes
that just simply will not be addressed
by the structural analysis alone
blue wanna add on that or we can
continue talking about this
yeah so i can say a couple things so i
think
agent-based modeling is
a super useful approach when you are
getting into systems that that are
multi-agent that
like are maybe predictive of any kind of
outcome
so like if this then that like how many
agents does it take to defect
um for a system to fail like you know if
if
um
everybody unloads their nfts all at once
then the system collapses right
so it's these kinds of things and and
what is the the cognitive
underpinnings what are the cognitive
underpinnings of the decision making in
an agent and because everybody's
influenced by a variety of factors uh
personal and environmental so agents can
start off
with like more of a of a different
disposition like than others
which is how we are in the real world
and um you know can have different
reactions to environmental cues
um and i think that that's all i'll say
about that
great point agent-based modeling is
really helpful for counter factual
analyses because we can ask well what
would be different if we had this many
instead of that many of this kind of
entity or if they could do this instead
of that
going back to the critical
infrastructure
and the need to design them reliably and
also de-risk against a variety of
failure modes
web 3 has some failure modes and threat
surfaces that are very similar to what
is seen in
web 2 and just other technological areas
and there's also some unique
and partially modeled scenarios in web 3
relating to blockchain and distributed
technologies specifically
and a lot of the complexities come from
the nested scales of decision making and
modeling that come into play in web3 so
just speaking coarsely there are
decisions and discourse at the level of
layer one chains themself like
blockchains or among blockchains as
we're observing in this uh current day
around the ethereum
changes that are happening known as the
merge but even within a layer one chain
there are multiple tokens and other
kinds of entities on that chain and
different communities that might be
using the same or different tokens or
their own tokens and teams and projects
that might be on chain or off chain so
there's a lot of interacting and nested
layers of analysis so considering how
different effects greetings jakob
how different effects of different
actors percolate through that kind of a
complex system is a key question
and we can talk about a few different
yaakov i'm going to make you
invited to speak
we can talk about a few different
modeling paradigms and approaches
and talk about what is state-of-the-art
and used wisely widely and wisely today
and then how cognitive modeling
specifically might be complementary and
empowering those methods
so
just speaking broadly i'm going to
mention smart contract auditing and then
top-down structural approaches and then
lastly bottom-up agentic approaches
which is the cognitive modeling approach
so first just speaking to smart contract
auditing smart contracts are familiar in
financial areas
and in kind of on-chain defy
applications
although smart contracts also underlie
technologies like dao and desai and
citations identity intellectual property
all kinds of aspects of society and
culture may be occurring through broadly
what are known as smart contracts
and the computational details of smart
contracts
can be audited along the lines of
security audits for other kinds of
computational programs for example a
hacker noon article describes that smart
contract auditing identifies any errors
in the code and ensures that the code is
safe to use when transferring funds
and so that kind of smart contract
auditing
is able to assess whether for example a
given reservoir of funds can be
extracted by an unauthorized user uh
that is absolutely valuable and we're
not suggesting that cognitive modeling
replaces that
we have two modes of systems modeling
beyond simple smart contract auditing
that are relevant and that's the
top-down structural modeling and the
bottom-up modeling perhaps jakob you
could describe
top-down and bottom-up approaches to
modeling here
yeah sure um
by the way i'm
on my phone right now because uh i uh
i'm just walking in the middle of uh the
city so if the background noise is too
loud just let me know
yeah on the so on the top down versus
bottom up approach i think the main um
the main
i guess
in classical cat cat modeling
the
one of the main approaches
is to
um identify the structure of the
of the system that's being studied in
this case it could be a decentralized
protocol that uh
enforces certain behaviors by smart
contracts
and
then this
kind of uh top-down structural modeling
is
diameter sweeps where we try to identify
all the different
um
all the different states that the system
can reach
and
but that doesn't really tell us anything
about what state the system will
actually reach and how it performs from
the perspective of its users
so the bottom up cognitive
sweeps
but
on the
okay lock up your audios a little bit
and now
more rigorous cognitive analysis from
the perspective of the
of the participants within that system
um
so
the idea behind
active block friends is to kind of
balance these two approaches and to take
insights from
um
from both
i hope that provides a brief overview
yep thank you i'll just kind of
summarize that because there was a
little bit of cutting in and out but the
top down in the structural approach to
modeling which is commonly used in
tokenomic suites like cad cad that was
mentioned by yakub
it describes system states
like the yield return percentage on some
kind of a smart contract and other
system parameters
and then it specifies the state spaces
which those parameters can exist in and
these tools also enable parameter
sweeping across those system parameters
and that's like a macro economic
analysis
that can be said to be taking like a
population level
approach to modeling the behaviors of
these complex systems so that would be
equivalent to like modeling a
macroeconomic sector with systems of
equations and then exploring how those
equations influence each other
and in contrast there is a bottom-up
agentic approach which entails a
cognitive model of the agents because
the cognitive model is
which we're using uh in the active
inference sense
of the generative model that provides
that agent with the ability to engage in
perception
cognition and action where cognition is
describing various
functionalities like memory preference
and action selection anticipation and so
on
so
we've been thinking about this angle of
cognitive modeling in web 3 a lot
because our project active block friends
is an open source package that is
explicitly addressing
and trying to enable this kind of
cognitive modeling in web 3.
um
and we're going to
have a bunch of time
to discuss
aspects of where cognitive modeling
could apply in web3
and i'm going to highlight um
three
areas
but we'll discuss them one by one and
also if anyone listening wants to join
they can absolutely feel welcome
and there's going to be three areas
or points of contact to explore so this
should be pretty fun and uh blue and
yuck up after each one of them like
please feel free to share how you see it
playing out or what you think is useful
about it so
here's reason one for why we'll argue
that web 3 needs cognitive modeling
it is that we need to understand the
consequences of single actions taken by
single actors
there are also singular events that
happen at the system level that we might
want to model like rare or really
important cascade type events like a
flipping
and that might be able to be modeled or
detected or designed around using
top-down structural approaches again
thinking about macroeconomics one could
imagine they have some dynamical
equations describing different
currencies and then they could identify
like a change point when one currency
flipped another that's the flipping
we're also interested in the potentially
cascading consequences
of single actions by single actors
so
this one specific transaction that this
one address sends to this one smart
contract is possibly able to induce
widespread consequences for the whole
system
and that level of atomic granularity in
terms of which entity did which
affordance which action
towards which entity
and then understanding the consequences
of that action at that granularity it
simply is inexpressible
within the structural or top-down mode
of modeling
which really can be said to abstract
over
individual entities and actions so we're
not denying that the structural the top
down
can provide an immensely
coarse-grained useful representation of
systems during design and implementation
but also we in this first point argue
that web 3 needs cognitive modeling
because we do want to model and
understand the consequences of single
actions that single actors take
blue or jacob
go ahead jacob if you have anything
there i will defect and wait until we
talk about multi-agent systems i think
yeah i think uh
i might add that
also there's also a lot of um
interesting overlap with um
the work on
computational
psychiatry or
other
kind of psychology oriented uh
models in the sense that these
um by analog by analyzing the cognitive
states
of agents
things like
how
uh what what are their levels of
curiosity within
within within a system or
um
is it
is
um
is the distribution of beliefs more
skewed towards uh
higher levels of uncertainty or
okay
your audio is just not too good yeah so
yeah but let me try to pick up with what
you mentioned about computational
psychiatry though
so
a top-down structural analysis of
computational psychiatry might be able
to say 10 percent of such and such group
have this
condition and of them then one percent
go on to do this and one percent of that
goes on to be this way
and so one could develop estimates like
per thousand people
with this characteristic
we can expect these outcomes as a health
care system or as an educational system
but again the level of expressivity or
granularity to describe
measurements coming from a given
individual like self-report or
measurements made of their brain and
their body
these kinds of measurements just don't
have a place in structural top-down
modeling so
it may be absolutely useful to take this
macroeconomic structural top-down
perspective to have population level
descriptives
however
the view from the inside the bottom up
in the agentic perspective
and to incorporate the kinds of data and
information which we have in the
blockchain case like individual
addresses making transactions
we need to have agent level modeling to
be able to
have that kind of a um
personalized clinical relationship
a personalized education relationship
or
making systems that account for what
individual actors expect prefer and can
do
rather than just designing systems only
at the level of system state space
parameters and then expecting that
somehow whatever it is that agents
expect or prefer preferrer can do will
simply work within that framework
okay so that was the first
point
about why web3 needs cognitive modeling
because again it's important to model
and understand the consequences of
single actions that single actors take
which might be extraordinarily rare or
improbable
and so we won't be able to have useful
top-down modeling of those kinds of
actions
here's a second point
we believe that web 3 needs cognitive
modeling because we want to consider
the function of web3 systems that are
not simply quantitative or financial for
example
science research education governance
all of these areas are not strictly
about number crunching
and so in these settings
knowledge and meaning which are based
around context and we could even say
that they're non-fungible
knowledge and meaning making of
epistemic entities
will not be engaged with by top-down
structural structural modeling or smart
contract auditing
because quite literally it is about the
situated entity
and their epistemic experience like the
kinds of
observations that they're making and how
that's updating their generative model
and then what that is
helping them to do so the way that that
would get shoehorned into a structural
model would be assume that
some percentage
of uh individuals are going to listen to
this podcast and then that makes some of
them
more likely to engage in this action so
that is again that view from the top
just like we explored in the
computational psychiatry case that view
from the top or a probabilistic way to
talk about the actions of groups
and this is the complementary view which
is the view from the bottom and this
second point is just to say that
especially if we're going to step beyond
quantitative and financial analyses
that these kinds of knowledge and
meeting meaning making behavior of
entities
are just doubly inaccessible unless we
have cognitive modeling so to design
appropriate
systems
for
science education governance
we will need to have models of what
individuals observe
believe prefer
and do rather than hoping that we can
simply specify the state space that the
system can exist in
and then let individuals run within that
framework
i'll follow up on that um i think that
like yes for
the um dsi but also systems like
regenerative finance will require
novel methods of accounting and so this
kind of cognitive modeling will enable
um i think what jakob was saying earlier
that maybe uh daniel you haven't touched
on yet but this parameter sweeping
so so like when
um
when a person values something whether
it's carbon credits or um you know
episodic knowledge
when
so when the value system differs from
dollars and cents
these kinds of
uh
ultimate accounting systems are enabled
or facilitated by this kind of cognitive
modeling like will these value systems
and structures work for these people and
you know multi-agent systems can have
variable value systems so i think that
these parameters will will greatly help
us to determine what kind of alternative
accounting structures would be
yes
and there's
many ways and it is by no means trivial
to incorporate these really rich and
expressive things that we want to say
about such systems into the model for
example even just in the example that
blue brought up with regenerative
finance
to describe how different individuals
are making different decisions that
might be a function of
differences in their capacities so their
affordances their capacities for action
it might also reflect different
attention
or different beliefs about the
consequences of different actions and so
there are vast combinations
of
cognitive models to explore and for that
reason being able to do parameter sweeps
across them which is what cad cad the
package enables is really valuable and
that's why active block for ins is
implementing active inference models in
cad cad because it provides a useful
and professional way to do some of these
functions that are just not part of
cognitive models in a narrow sense
like being able to do parameter sweeps
being able to specify the execution
orders
but that's a bit more on the technical
side of active block rinse which
definitely we encourage people to
learn more and get involved with and
help with
i'll just go to this third yes blue
ohio
yeah if i could just uh quickly follow
up on that on the notion of parameter
sweeps i think they also serve two kinds
of functions on the one hand
it's for um predictive purposes so
um
designing models and
of different organizational systems
and running multiple simulations to
evaluate the different consequences of
that system but on the on the other hand
we it can also serve an
explanatory purpose where by we want to
evaluate the state of an already
existing system
uh given
data on the blockchain so
what active
uh what the formalism of active
inference allows us to do is to take
data from the blockchain on the
different actions that different agents
take or actors within the system take
and then do a parameter sweep over their
beliefs to identify which set of beliefs
make their actions base optimal
and once we identify that set of beliefs
we can do further analysis
on
what
that means uh from a cognitive sense
in what what would that mean in
different different scenarios
and uh do this kind of more uh this
retrospective analysis of the system and
one more thing on the
on the voting mechanisms just to give an
example
i think there's
an increasing um
increasing uh or it is increasingly
mentioned that quadratic voting is
a more optimal
optimal paradigm for
for voting and governance in general
but
why why does it have
why is it quadratic why isn't there an
uh
um third exponent or fourth exponent
and
these kinds of questions i think can be
answered through cognitive modeling
where we can evaluate the trade-off
between
a
higher mathematical complexity where
the operation itself
uh
at more cognitive constraint and the
actual results
when
the agents act within that voting system
so
um just wanted to give this
example of how can be used in a purely
non-monetary
governance type setting
nice points you laid out a lot of the
kind of modeling pipeline which is that
the blockchains themself
actually already contain the exact kind
of agent level empirical data that we
want and it's even structured in the way
that we want to take it in which is like
which entity which address
did what and then what was the
consequence of the action
so indeed that information is already on
chain and summarized in a way that's
amenable to fitting cognitive parameters
so the question of how to determine
which cognitive models are relevant is
it's indeed a challenge
but at the same time the data that is
input is of the right type to fit
various cognitive models
that could be useful for example some
hidden state that describes how somebody
uh how much attention somebody is paying
to a given given governance system as
overall and then also being able to sub
specify
um at a given time or changing through
time
their preferences on a variety of topics
and that's exactly what allows the
counter factual analysis or exploring
like alternate futures because we could
ask well what if people were paying more
attention is that an important area to
go or should it be
explored to modify not the attention
being paid to this issue but rather how
much they know about it so
nice um point there so for financial and
for non-financial systems
where entity level knowledge and meaning
making is relevant which it arguably
always is
that is an important opening for
cognitive modeling and this view from
the inside to complement the top-down
structural modeling
okay
um
i'm gonna just mention the third of the
points and then in the rest of the hour
we can hear some different questions
different thoughts so anyone who wants
to speak thanks for requesting
and
the uh third point
is that we argue that cognitive modeling
can complement
traditional computational security
analyses so that it's like static and
dynamic analysis of smart contracts
and those kinds of analyses can be
complemented
by
exploring in a test net or in a sandbox
setting
what happens when that smart contract is
deployed in realistic settings which is
to say interacting with other contracts
and interacting with individuals who
might differ in their capacities
preferences expectations and so on
so just to kind of give a example that
seems relevant here
smart contract analysis could determine
if there was a contract which was
supposed to hold funds securely and only
be able to take in one or two kinds of
tokens like a vending machine you can
put dollars in and then soda comes out
or you put soda in and dollars comes out
so potentially like a a liquidity pool
based swap
now
stand-alone analysis of that smart
contract could absolutely tell you
whether it was possible for somebody who
shouldn't be able to access those funds
was able to access those funds
there are also failure modes and risks
associated with that smart contract in
operation
that can't be said to be within the
smart contract rather they're in the
relationship of that smart contract with
others for example
other contracts or exchanges that are
handling that token might be engaged in
arbitrage relationships
once we think about social media and
information sharing that happens
off-came there might even be narrative
or news based events
which make it so that that smart
contract's ability to hold the funds
is great and enabling however still in
the realized application of the contract
it is functionally getting rugged as
well
and so these are all areas that we want
to
explore more
with the active block fence package as
we kind of build in these modules to
consider it
and do case study analysis but that is
just to
close
this
section of the discussion as we now open
up to more broader discussion and just
to restate that three of the key areas
we think
cognitive modeling uh can play a role in
web 3 are first understanding the
consequences of single actions by single
actors
second by expanding the scope of web 3
systems that we consider and design for
to be systems that aren't simply
quantitative and financial so
considering research education
governance and so on
and then lastly complementing
computational security analyses
with emulations and simulations
scenarios and counterfactuals
of how different aspects of cyber
physical systems might play out in
specific testable settings
so
thanks for
making it along this far and now we can
just
talk about whatever people would like to
go towards right
thank you so
one of the things that's on my mind is
that
this
is maybe abstracting away
um
an important
layer that
we're not really speaking about whether
we're doing
bottom up modeling or top down and that
is
you know that there are
miso or middle level
structures that are relevant
to cognitive
modeling in terms of you know
communities
cultures
organizations and they have an influence
on the mental model that a person has
very explicitly by just talking about
a wallet a wallet might belong to an
individual or it might belong
to an entity but their behaviors will
tend
to be
different might not even know
perhaps whether it is an individual or
some other sort of entity that's behind
a wallet
but i think it gets more tricky
to think about
well you know what is the environment in
which that entity that has the wallet
exists in
like
what
culture
what regulatory
regime like what communities are they
part of and i don't necessarily know how
that should be done but it seems like
that is an important part of
the context
that influences
the model that any agent
has in choosing whatever transactions
they make with their wallet and so
maybe we have to
think about how to address that or if
you have thoughts about how that should
work they haven't
thank you ray for this
comment
about the miso scale and i think there's
just a few points to add on that
structural specifications of systems
they identify really important system
level parameters
but then it can often be challenging to
add in
other parameters because the models are
composable only with macro aspects
so it becomes hard to compose models
that are taking a purely top down as
well as a purely bottom-up angle
where cognitive modeling might help us
explore that middle
is that it makes a specific distinction
between observed and unobserved aspects
of systems so hidden states are
unobserved states
the observed behavior in a blockchain
setting are like the transactions that
happen on chain
and then
you're right that there's so much
context that is unobserved in that one
data artifact that would be relevant to
know about and so we can think about two
cases where this context is either used
or not
the first case is where we actually have
no other context
in that situation we can still do
intentional stance modeling towards
unknown types of actors like we don't
know what is behind this address
but we know that they engage with this
kind of a pattern
and it's not enough just to take a
top-down perspective and say well this
many people interacted with this
contract or the average was two times
per day because that two times per day
might be
the average of
a small fraction that interact 100 times
per day and some that interact
infrequently so cognitive modeling first
would help us take an intentional and a
strategic stance
in the absence of context
and then
context as we add it in
can become useful so we might know that
multiple addresses are under the control
of a given team or individual or we
might have access to connecting
the social media profile of somebody who
puts it in their ens
profile
or page
that
could be composable at the agent level
and uh
i don't think that's an answer at all so
open to whatever else people add
um
because the meso is where the complexity
is
and we would just
expect and prefer
that the composability of specifying
different kinds of entities not just on
chain entities but also teams
organizations and so on
that that will
enable these kinds of models to do
exploration and parameter sweeps in that
exact space you described
thank you
i would maybe also add to that
that as
the
toolbox itself
uh gets expanded and different
um
different computational models um are
added
i think it's
the
the case where we want to distinguish
between an actor that's actually
a single single human versus a team of
people controlling a multi multi-sig
should technically be reflected
in the underlying data to some uh to
some extent say if uh if for instance
you want to analyze um
you want to use cognitive modeling to
analyze a certain dow and you have a
list of all the different addresses
as you
perform this kind of multi-agent
model or even try to
fit the
the belief states of each of the wallets
given
given the prior data
it should become evident that certain
that certain wallets perhaps are
operating at slightly different time
scales or
um
or are
or are maintained are uh are updating
their beliefs at uh
again at different time scales or in a
slightly different way than the other
agents and they're and then we might
also do some cross-correlation between
the belief states of the individual
actors about which we perhaps know that
they are individual actors
and the agents that we are not sure
whether they
represent a single uh
entity or a group of people
uh so i think
that
a lot of it might
already implicitly be available
uh within within the current toolbox but
as we add more algorithms that do more
efficient
uh computations and
different schemes of performing uh
belief updates and
the leaf search
i think
that's a very interesting
area to explore as well
thanks jacob brock
you want to add anything
um yeah i think jacob's point here about
you know having
some
verified data
sources
and having these kinds of generalities
about how
one kind of data source looks like for
one kind of agent versus another kind
it's you know
more of an organization or a syndicate
or some some other kind of non-singular
individual
um is
uh
correct um
and i think that this idea of you know
the meso scale
being missed generally speaking and
modeling is also correct
um
but i and i i think that
cognitive modeling in general
affords
partially i guess a solution to really
this meso both of these problems are
really related to like the oracle
problem
of just where does data come from and
who you trust and all this sort of stuff
um
because even if you get this culture
data it's like
you know what's what's in the water
what's in the food what's
this business doing with
you know what are the externalities of
this process or whatever yeah there's a
lot of still
unknown data and the only way
that we currently have to kind of
model that
effectively
is with essentially a cognitive sort of
model that um like you mentioned daniel
has this distinction between
observed and unobserved or hidden states
and
um
you know known
uh states to the system and so um
it's never
i guess to frame it it's it's like
security is this cat and mouse game
really we're in this now in this
cognitive security cat and mouse game
and we're just going to go further into
that but
you know
is a
large corporation or
whatever some some syndicate whatever
trying to
maybe obscure their
you know
behavior on chain like
so that they're harder to
predict for some reason
um
probably things like that will
they already occur in the political
context today
i'm sure that it will continue and
decentralize in that fashion and so
it will
just be
a
baseline this will just be table stakes
to do cognitive modeling to have any
kind of grip
on something like prediction or
discernibility of of these kinds of
systems
nice very
interesting
so in the last 10 minutes we can
[Music]
have any speakers join or people can ask
questions
this is happening during the ongoing
git coin funding round gr15
and
we have a
grant in for this project which is
supportable as well as many other
awesome
public goods and produce projects that
people can check out
and
on the grant page you'll see some
recent discussions we've had with
cadcad community and with the smart
contract research forum where we talked
about a few
different ongoing steps
the current status of the package is
that it's it's available it's an open
source package
and it is framed as notebooks primarily
made by jakob
that are like the perception cognition
and action
of an entity in an abstract grid space
which sounds and basically is
general and abstract
so some of our next steps are to bring
that machinery
and that approach
to
take in the kinds of empirical data that
are relevant for blockchain systems
so that's one key area
as well as well as um improving the
functionality of the package through
various means like
improved ability to visualize
outcomes of models to specify models and
sweep across them
to have documentation and other
integrations that will just make it a
better package and more useful
um
i guess in the last 10 minutes there's a
few other ways to go but i'll pause if
anyone has any thoughts or questions
the point i wanted to add in and then
again
anyone can feel free to add is that
using active inference as a scale-free
or skill-friendly framework as we
sometimes say
in advantage of it is that we can talk
about
perception cognition and action
for different entities this is not
creating a little brain for individuals
only people
this is about being able to look at how
decisions are enacted
in different kinds of organizations
and those organizations could be
cellular biological organizations like
humans
or it could be organizations
that you suspect something complex is
happening within but you're only seeing
the tip of the iceberg on chain
or it could be organizations that are
entirely on chain
and so that's one of the reasons why
it's important to have
a really flexible modeling framework
like active inference for cognitive
systems because it's not bound to for
example only human emotions and sensory
processing it enables us to describe a
wide variety of systems in a cognitive
fashion which is what we've explored in
our eos work
active entity ontology for science
so that is where we see active inference
as a leading cognitive modeling
framework
and natural fit for this cyber physical
space
and then the other pillar of the active
block furnace project other than active
inference is cad cad which was mentioned
earlier and cad cad
has been used in a wide range of token
modeling and engineering settings
you can see actually their
ethereum validator models which have
been publicly available for uh several
years i don't know the exact date but
the um
work on cad cad modeling
of the f proof of stake
transition
has been in the works for a really long
time and that kind of gives a
a taste of
from the outside
speaking personally
of what it looks like to use
formal system models
over long time scales
to strategize and de-risk
really complex decisions that groups and
individuals make
and
that is still at the structural level
so it's one thing to be able to scan
across different
validator reward systems or percentages
and ask what would happen
if a certain parameter is set to three
or two or one
again it's quite a different thing to
ask how
entities with different attentions and
preferences
will make certain decisions
and so it'd be like the equivalent of a
macroeconomic change being induced like
we raised the interest rate by one
percent
our macroeconomic curve intersection
models show that that should increase
consumer spending by this much
but
that consumer spending even if it is an
accurate prediction from the structural
modeling
it is enacted by individuals making
decisions
in response to those common system
parameters
so that highlights that the agentic
perspective is complementary to the
systems and the structural description
but we really think that it's going to
bring a level of depth
and also new challenges because the
state space of all cognitive parameters
and how they interact is truly vast
so it will not be necessarily the the
shortest or simplest road
but we think it's going to be one of the
most meaningful
because it's going to bring new function
to
different web 3 ecosystems and
subsystems
that otherwise would have totally
incommensurate models
the d5 models are not going to apply to
dow decision making and those are not
going to apply to science and how that
works and having some kind of an
interoperable layer
for what entities are doing what
is going to be
enabling really rich modeling of web 3
ecosystems
now can web 3 survive without cognitive
modeling
i don't know we could vote
but we we provocatively raised the
question i think um jakob and brock and
others in some meetings with with this
framing because
we we do want to
suggest or at least raise
this notion
that no amount
of top level systems engineering
unless it's complemented by a bottom-up
perspective on what are the capacities
attentions preferences and so on of
entities in this world
the embodied natural ones as well as
like computational artifacts you know a
runaway decision making ai with a
trading balance
all these kinds of systems that we have
to model including systems that we don't
even know what type they are necessarily
we need
interoperable and expressive ways to
describe those systems so that's why we
think that
web3 with cognitive modeling can survive
and without we just don't know
i have another question
i think it relates
fundamentally to potential biases in a
model given
data availability
so
um it's very clear always what data is
available like what transactions are on
chain or what
prices are
paid
in market for securities or commodity
what have you but
there is actually a lot that occurs
in
society which is not necessarily
a market type
activity with with hard data associated
with it and
how does
a cognitive
model
account for the fact that that many
things are missed and that we we simply
overlook
many aspects of things that for instance
might be called the the gift economy
where people just informally
do things for each other and it's
not really
recorded anywhere i mean it is truly
part of the representation of our
individual cognitive models for how we
exist in the world but where is this
going to make it into any model that we
try to do
it's a great
question and it's a thread i hope we
keep alive even beyond this space ending
in a few minutes so no answer we'll do
it justice but i'll give some thoughts
one is the difference between
observables in our model empirical data
that we're reading in
and unobservables which are considered
factors but not necessarily ones where
we have data points either because we
just haven't added those data points in
or maybe they don't even exist in
principle so
various kinds of features can be
observed and various can't be so it's
important to have a framework that deals
with both and then the second point is
that it may be possible for some kind of
like out in the open models to use some
kinds of totally out in the open data
but then let's just say that within the
context of a given community of care
people consented to having their
information
digested or summarized
and used to augment a community-specific
model
so the provenance and the um
use of that data
that would be potentially speaking to
these more authentic inorganic social
interactions
those kinds of data
could be grafted or fused
with more open source
templates dealing with open data
so there'd be a lot of opportunity for
model templates
and some precomputed public goods type
data sets
to then be enriched
on the edges
by different communities that we're
going to be bringing in specific
data types
and the the path has been in a way
blazed forward by cad cad
where the package is open source
and many of their models are open source
yet
they're also able to engage with clients
in a consulting capacity using
models that are not fully open source
probably or data sets that aren't fully
available
so it's one reason why we
are uh
strongly open source with the package
while also recognizing that a lot of the
last mile use cases might bring in data
that isn't strictly open source in the
same way that this code should be
okay well
thanks for listening everyone
please uh head over to
i guess our twitter profile to learn
more
about our ongoing bitcoin grant
you